Guide to the Max Putzel Papers Relating to William Marion Reedy and The Mirror
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Max Putzel papers relating to William Marion Reedy and The Mirror
1907-1963
1954-1963
YCAL MSS 689
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.16
(10 boxes)
The collection consists of Max Putzel's research materials on St. Louis-area journalist William Marion Reedy and drafts of Putzel's biography of Reedy, The Man In the Mirror (1963). Putzel's research materials include the following: subject files containing photomechanical copies of articles from The Mirror and other publications, including work by Reedy and others, original newspaper clippings, and correspondence, including copies of letters from Reedy to others and letters to and from Putzel; index cards containing Putzel's autograph manuscript notes and bibliographic information; and miscellaneous copies of The Mirror and copies of essays by Reedy. Writings include an outline and paper submitted by Putzel for courses taken at Washington University in St. Louis in the mid 1950s and a draft and setting copy of Putzel's book-length biography of Reedy.
Putzel, Max
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Max Putzel, 1964. For additional information consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
William Marion Reedy (1862-1920)
William Marion Reedy, a well-known American journalist, was born December 11, 1862 in St. Louis, Missouri to Patrick and Anne (Marion) Reedy and raised on the north side of St. Louis in a mostly Irish-American neighborhood called Kerry Patch. Reedy attended Christian Brothers College (1880) and then took his first journalism job with the Missouri Republican. Reedy moved on to the St. Louis Globe-Democrat, where he started out as a court reporter and then focused on feature writing. During his twenty years at the paper, he also wrote articles for other publications, including the Sunday Mirror, which he took over and renamed Reedy's Mirror. Reedy died July 28, 1920 in San Francisco, California.
Biographical information taken from "William Marion Reedy." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2002. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 10 Jan. 2013.
Max Putzel (1910-2003)
Max Putzel, born April 5, 1910 in Denver, Colorado to Henry V. and Helen (Renard) Putzel, grew up in New Rochelle, New York and St. Louis, Missouri before earning a bachelor's degree from Yale University in 1932. After graduating from Yale, Putzel took a job at the Granite City, Illinois Press-Record and then the St. Louis Post-Dispatch, where he worked as a copy boy, feature writer, and drama editor. In the late 1930s and early 1940s Putzel worked as an associate editor at Common Sense magazine in New York and then spent the war years working for the U.S. State Department's Office of Inter-American Affairs. When the war ended, Putzel became a farmer, first in Virginia, where he worked as a tenant farmer, then in the Meramec River Valley west of St. Louis, where he bought and worked a family farm. He attended Washington University in the mid 1950s and returned to Yale in the late 1950s for a doctorate in English. Putzel then taught English and American literature at the University of Connecticut for two decades. Putzel was the author of The Man in the Mirror (1963), a biography of newspaper editor William Marion Reedy, and Genius of Place: William Faulkner's Triumphant Beginnings (1985). Putzel died August 19, 2003.
Biographical information taken from obituary published in the Hartford Courant, August 23, 2003 and "Max Putzel." Contemporary Authors Online. Detroit: Gale, 2002. Gale Biography In Context. Web. 10 January 2013.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of Max Putzel's research materials on St. Louis-area journalist William Marion Reedy and drafts of Putzel's biography of Reedy, The Man in the Mirror (1963). Putzel's research materials include the following: subject files containing photomechanical copies of articles from The Mirror and other publications, including work by Reedy and others, original newspaper clippings, and correspondence, including copies of letters from Reedy to others and letters to and from Putzel; index cards containing Putzel's autograph manuscript notes and bibliographic information; and miscellaneous copies of The Mirror and copies of essays by Reedy. Writings in the collection include an outline and paper submitted by Putzel for courses taken at Washington University in St. Louis in the mid 1950s and a draft and setting copy of Putzel's book-length biography of Reedy.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Research Material, 1907-1963. II. Writings, 1954-1963.
The Mirror, St. Louis; Mirror (Saint Louis, Mo.); American literature -- 20th Century; Journalists -- United States; Periodicals -- United States; Saint Louis (Mo.); Journalists -- United States -- 20th cenntury; Putzel, Max ( Man in The mirror); Reedy, William Marion, 1862-1920
- Research Material, 1907-1963; Series I; 4.66; (8 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Subject Files, Index Cards, and Other Material.
  Scope and Contents
  The research materials include subject files, index cards, and writings relating to Max Putzel's work on William Marion Reedy and The Mirror. The subject files consist chiefly of photomechanical copies of articles from The Mirror and other publications, including work by Reedy and others, as well as original newspaper clippings and correspondence. Correspondence includes (copies of) letters from Reedy and letters to and from Putzel. The index cards contain Putzel's autograph manuscript notes and bibliographic information. Other materials include miscellaneous copies of The Mirror and copies of essays by Reedy.
  - Subject Files
    - Akins, Zoe, 1907-1958, undated (Box 1)
    - Atherton, Gertude, undated (Box 1)
    - Beardsley, Aubrey, undated (Box 1)
    - Bellamy, Edward, undated (Box 1)
    - Bernays, Thekla, undated (Box 1)
    - Bibliog[raphical] Notes, undated (Box 1)
    - Bierce, Ambrose, undated (Box 1)
    - Bloch, Albert, undated (Box 1)
    - Braithwaite, William Stanley (copies), 1915-1917 (Box 1)
    - Braun, W. C., 1953, undated (Box 1)
    - Bruner, R. W., 1959 June 6 (Box 1)
    - Bryan, William Jennings, undated (Box 1)
    - Byars, William Vincent, 1959, undated (Box 1)
    - Cable, George W., undated (Box 1)
    - Carman, Bliss, undated (Box 1)
    - Chopin, Kate, undated (Box 1)
    - Churchill, Winston, undated (Box 1)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1963 April 8 (Box 1)
    - Cowper, William, undated (Box 1)
    - Crane, Stephen, undated (Box 1)
    - "D" general, undated (Box 1)
    - Dreiser & Reedy, 1959, undated (Box 1)
    - Ederheimer, Richard, undated (Box 1)
    - Filley, Cle[?] Ives, undated (Box 1)
    - Forty-Eight, Committee of, undated (Box 1)
    - "G" general, 1915, undated (Box 1)
    - Garland, Hamlin, undated (Box 1)
    - George, Henry, undated (Box 1)
    - Godkin, E. L., undated (Box 1)
    - "H" general (empty), undated (Box 1)
    - Hawthorne, Nathaniel (empty), undated (Box 1)
    - Hubbard, Elbert, undated (Box 1)
    - Huebsch, B. W., undated (Box 1)
    - Imperialism 1896-, undated (Box 1)
    - Kennerley, Mitchell, undated (Box 1)
    - LaBeaume, Louis, 1916-1918 (Box 1)
    - Lawrence, J. J., undated (Box 1)
    - Lindsay, Vachel, undated (Box 1)
    - Li[erature], Amer[ican], undated (Box 1)
    - Loomis, Roger Sherman, undated (Box 1)
    - Lowell, Amy, undated (Box 2)
    - Masters, ----, undated (Box 2)
    - "McGaffey-Reedy autograph", 1905 (Box 2)
    - McIntyre, Minnie, undated (Box 2)
    - McKinley, William, undated (Box 2)
    - Mirror bibliography, undated (Box 2)
    - Mosher, Thos., undated (Box 2)
    - "P" general (empty), undated (Box 2)
    - Pollard, Joseph Percival, undated (Box 2)
    - "R/Biog/Bauday", undated (Box 2)
    - "R/Biog/St. L. Post-Dispatch", undated (Box 2)
    - "R/Biog/St. Louis Univ. Mag." (empty), undated (Box 2)
    - Religion (empty), undated (Box 2)
    - (Rudy) Biog[raphy], 1941, undated (Box 2)
    - Rudy Poems, undated (Box 2)
    - Rudy Works, undated; 3 (Box 2)
    - Ruskin, John, undated (Box 2)
    - "S" general, undated (Box 2)
    - St. Louis, undated (Box 2)
    - Sappho, undated (Box 2)
    - [Scherz?], Carl (empty), undated (Box 2)
    - Sienkiewicz, Henrik, undated (Box 2)
    - Style, undated (Box 2)
    - "T" general, undated (Box 2)
    - Teasdale, Sara, undated; 2 (Box 2)
    - Tietjens, Eunice, undated (Box 2)
    - Tolstoy, Leo, undated (Box 2)
    - Verlaine, Paul, undated (Box 2)
    - Voynich, E. L., undated (Box 2)
    - Wescott, E. M., undated (Box 2)
    - Whitman, [Walt], undated (Box 2)
    - Wilde, Oscar, undated (Box 2)
    - Winkler, Jean, undated (Box 2)
    - Women, undated (Box 2)
    - Yeats, W. B. (copy), undated (Box 2)
  - Index Cards
    - Introduction - Dreiser, [circa 1954-1963] (Box 3)
    - Dunbar - Magazine, [circa 1954-1963] (Box 4)
    - Newspapers - Realism, [circa 1954-1963] (Box 5)
    - Reedy - Twain, [circa 1954-1963] (Box 6)
    - U - Zola, [circa 1954-1963] (Box 7)
  - Other Material, 0.42; (1 box)
    - Miscellaneous copies of The Mirror, undated; 2 (Box 8)
    - "Selected essays by WMR", undated; 8 (Box 8)
- Writings, 1954-1963; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series II. Writings contains an outline and paper for courses at Washington University in 1954-1955 and a draft and setting copy of Putzel's biography of William Marion Reedy, The Man in the Mirror (1963).
  - "Mirror Study Outline", 1954, undated (Box 8)
  - "Manifest Destiny Through a Mid-Western Mirror: William Marion Reedy's Changing Ideas on American Imperialism Around 1898," typescript, corrected, 1955 (Box 8)
  - The Man in the Mirror, draft, typescript carbon, corrected, 1962; 2 (Box 9)
  - The Man in the Mirror, setting copy, typescript, corrected, 1963; 3 (Box 9)
- Oversize, 0.08; (1 box)
  - Clipping relating to Zoe Akins (In Series I), 1958 November 25 (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Clipping relating to William Vincent Byars (In Series I), 1959 July 29 (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Clippings relating to Commmittee of 48 (In Series I), undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Copies of letters to Mitchell Kennerley (In Series I), undated (Box 10 Oversize)
  - Clippings relating to Oscar Wilde (In Series I), undated (Box 10 Oversize)